Guide to the Paolo Valesio Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Paolo Valesio papers
1957-2009
MS 1594
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
55.75
(63 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, writings, and teaching files of Paolo Valesio.
Valesio, Paolo, 1939-
Conditions Governing Access
The original accession and Accessions 1992-M-048 through 2007-M-062 are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
All other accessions open for research.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by accession.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paolo Valesio, 1990-2007, and 2010.
Biographical / Historical
Paolo Valesio, poet and Italian language and literature scholar, was born in Bologna, Italy, in 1939. He was educated at the University of Bologna, and has held teaching positions at the University of Bologna, Harvard University, and New York University. He began teaching in the Department of Italian Language and Literature at Yale University in 1976 and had served as department chairman and director of graduate studies during his tenure. Valesio retired as an emeritus professor before joining the Department of Italian at Columbia University in 2005.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, writings, and teaching files of Paolo Valesio.
Italian language -- Study and teaching; Italian literature -- History and criticism; Rhetoric -- Philosophy; Valesio, Paolo, 1939-
- Original Accession
  Conditions Governing Access
  The material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
  - Correspondence, 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 366)
  - Correspondence: Personal documents, 1976-1981 (Box 2, Folder 366)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 366)
  - Essays, writings, 1968-1980s (Box 3, Folder 366)
  - Unpublished novel, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 366)
  - Personal documents, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 366)
  - Original typescript of published novel, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 366)
  - Short stories, 1972-1979 (Box 3, Folder 366)
  - Collection of poems, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 366)
  - Scholarly articles, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 366)
  - Original material pertaining to book published in 1980 (Box 4, Folder 366)
  - Original material pertaining to book published in 1980 (Box 5, Folder 366)
  - Scholarly articles, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 366)
  - Essays, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 366)
  - Notes for Italian dictionary: Reviews, articles, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 366)
  - Course materials (NYU), 1971 (Box 6, Folder 366)
  - Course materials, 1972-1973, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 366)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1974, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 366)
  - Scholarly articles, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 366)
  - Linguistics and rhetoric, Mid 1960s-mid 1970s (Box 8, Folder 366)
  - Linguistics and rhetoric, Mid 1960s-mid 1970s (Box 9, Folder 366)
  - Linguistics and rhetoric, Mid 1960s-mid 1970s (Box 10, Folder 366)
  - Novel proofs, Late 1960s (Box 11, Folder 366)
  - Collection of poems (Box 11, Folder 366)
  - Linguistics and rhetoric (manuscript and related material) (Box 11, Folder 366)
  - Linguistics and philology (Box 11, Folder 366)
  - Novel on rhetoric (Box 11, Folder 366)
  - Abstracts (Box 11, Folder 366)
  - Linguistics and rhetoric, Late 1960s (Box 12, Folder 366)
  - Material for book on Rabelais, 1973-1974 (Box 12, Folder 366)
  - Novel on rhetoric (Box 12, Folder 366)
  - Rabelais book, 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 366)
  - Linguistics and rhetoric, Early 1970s (Box 13, Folder 366)
  - Rhetorical essays, 1970s (Box 13, Folder 366)
  - Correspondence, 1970s (Box 13, Folder 366)
  - Correspondence, mostly pertaining to dissertations, 1985-1988 (Box 14, Folder 366)
  - Correspondence, financial records, personal papers, student transcripts, and evaluations of graduate students, 1979-1988 (Box 15, Folder 366)
- Additional Material, 1957-1989, undated; Accession 1992-M-048; 3; 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Carol King, 1992 May
  Received from: Paolo Valesio, 1992 Jan 6
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Course materials, 1961-1964, undated (Box 1)
  - University of Bologna: student government, cultural programs, Circa 1961 (Box 1)
  - Awards, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Writings, drafts Ascoltare il Silenzio (Box 2)
  - Writings, poetry, 1957, 1962-1987, undated (Box 3)
  - Dissertation, Circa 1961 (Box 3)
- Additional Material, 1978-1992, undated; Accession 1993-M-040; 1.75; 2 boxes
  Addition inventory by Carol King, 1993 Feb
  Received from: Paolo Valesio, 1993 Jan 13
  - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Poesie Regalate, 1978-1992, undated (Box 2)
- Additional Material, 1974-1993; Accession 1994-M-005
  Addition inventory by Carol King, 1993 Jul
  Received from: Paolo Valesio, 1993 Jul 14
  - Council on West European Studies, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Graduate studies: dissertation evaluations, fellowship awards, teaching appointments, admission rank lists, comprehensive examinations, course lists, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
  - Undergraduate studies, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Materiali e illustrazioni, I-V: materials pertaining to public lectures given by Paolo Valesio, 1974-1993 (Box 1)
  - Whitney Humanities Center, 1987-1992 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1957-1993; Accession 1995-M-014
  Addition inventory by Carol King, 1994 Jul
  Received from: Paolo Valesio, 1994 Jul 28
  - Correspondence (9 folders), 1992 (Box 1)
  - Literary annotation materials (2 folders), 1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Material pertaining to Valesio's cultural activities: biographical material, 1957-1969, 1976 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1996-M-032
  - Correspondence, 1992 December-1993 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts of others [many critiqued by Paolo Valesio], 1994-1995, undated (Box 1)
  - Curricula vitae of others, 1987-1992, undated (Box 1)
  - Gabriele D'Annunzio: The Dark Flame, by Paolo Valesio [annotated drafts, publishers' galley proofs], 1992 (Box 2)
  - "Gabriele D'Annunzio: His Writings, His Times" [an international symposium held at Yale University], 1987 March 26-29 (Box 2)
  - "P. Paolo Pasolini: A Meeting Five Years Later" [a symposium held at Yale University], 1980 October 23-26 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 1996-M-118
  - Topical files
    - Politics [independent newspapers], 1968, undated (Box 1)
    - Religion [publications, announcements of religious and humanitarian organizations], 1990-1996 (Box 1)
    - Theater [programs, handbills, reviews]
      - 1958-1968 (Box 1)
      - 1990-1996 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 1997-M-038
  - Correspondence and departmental files [14 folders], 1992-1994 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1998-M-007
  - Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Submitted texts with annotations, Circa 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Council on West European Studies, 1990-1994 (Box 1)
  - Romance philology project, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Undergraduate studies, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Grade lists, papers, recommendations, curricula vitae (Box 1)
  - Admissions, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Graduate students, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Dissertation prospectuses, 1993 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1998-M-106
  - Correspondence, departmental files, annotated literary texts, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-089
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Departmental files, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - MLA interviews, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - "BiGLI,", 1993 (Box 1)
  - Materiali e illustrazioni, VI-VII [materials pertaining to lectures given by Paolo Valesio], 1993-1997 (Box 1)
  - "Literatura y traduccion" [course], 1996 (Box 1)
  - "Parole Ambulante" [poetry festival], 1996 (Box 1)
  - Francis of Assisi Film Fest, 1994 (Box 1)
  - "Nuove Lettere", 1992 (Box 1)
  - "Massarosa", 1992 (Box 1)
  - "Quicentenary Encounter: Italian and American Poetry" [symposium], 1992 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts of others [many critiqued by Paolo Valesio], 1997-1998 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-136
  - Correspondence, religious flyers, and theater flyers, 1998-1999, undated (Box 1)
  - The Green Rose [annotated draft of English translation], undated (Box 2)
  - Yale Poetry Group, 1993-1998, undated (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2001-M-015
  - Administrative correspondence/files, 1983-1984, 1990-1999, (1998-1999) bulk (Box 1)
  - Submitted literary texts with annotations and accompanying correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Religious and theatrical flyers, 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - Yale Poetry Group, 1998-2000 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-002
  - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Acting Director of Graduate Studies, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Yale seminar, 1999 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-039
  - Correspondence, letteraria, 1968-1996 (Box 1)
  - Testi regalati, 1999-2001 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-061
  - Correspondence [personal, professional], 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  - Subject files
    - Academy of American Poets, 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Directed readings, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
    - Dissertation reports, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 16-20)
    - Independent study, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Italian 315: Ethics and Narrative, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Luzi, Alfredo, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Staff
      - Centovalli, Benedetta, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Holmes, Olivia, 1996-199 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Nigro, S. Silvano, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Rigoni, Mario Andrea, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Senior administrative assistant search, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Whitney Humanities Center, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-001
  - Correspondence, letteraria, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-025
  - Literary correspondence, 1995-2000 (inclusive), 1999-2000 (bulk) (Box 1)
  - Testi regalati, 1998-2002 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-004
  - Correspondence [personal, professional], 1996-2001 (Box 1)
  - Departmental files [includes staffing, courses, projects, memoes, etc.], 1991-2001 (Box 1)
  - Graduate School director (DGS) [includes comprehensives], 1985-1993, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Curricula vitae, 1984-2001 (Box 1)
  - Letters of recommendation, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Letters of recommendation, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts, annotated, 2001-2003 (Box 2)
  - Printed materials pertaining to religion and theater, 1993-2002 (Box 2)
  - Yale Poetry Group, 2001-2002 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-050
  - Office correspondence, 1989-2000 (Box 1)
  - Editorial projects, 1998-2001, undated (Box 1)
  - Materials for Gabriele D'Annunzio: the Dark Flame [1990?], undated (Box 2)
  - Writings and poetry of Paolo Valesio [includes notes, drafts, printed material], 1960-1997, undated (Box 3)
  - Writings and poetry of Paolo Valesio [includes notes, drafts, printed material], 1960-1997, undated (Box 4)
- Additional Material, Accession 2005-M-002
  - Yale Italian Poetry (YIP), 1996-2000 (Box 1)
  - Italian Poetry Society of America (IPSA), 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Poetry groups, drafts of poems, 1987-2004 (Box 2–3)
  - Poetry selections [includes La Rosa Verde, L'Odore del Sangue ], 1988, 1991 (Box 4)
  - La Poesia ante el tercer milenio: poesia de las lenguas y lengua de la poesia [international seminar], 2000 November (Box 5)
  - Literary correspondence, 1994-1999 (Box 5)
  - Writings
    - [includes Dardi, Volcano in Cento, La Vestizione, Il Regno Doloroso], 1999-2002, undated (Box 5)
    - [includes Il Viso, Angel Mateau, Rosa Verd e, La Campagna dell'Ottantasette (III), 1987, 1990, undated (Box 6)
  - Departmental correspondence/files, 1989-1995, undated (Box 7)
  - Literary and administrative correspondence, 1975-2003 (Box 8)
  - Literary correspondence/cultural materials, 2001-2003 (Box 9)
  - Dissertation prospectuses (Prospetti III), undated (Box 10)
  - La Cambialavoro [translation/drafts], 1995-1996 (Box 10)
  - Tradimenti [drafts], 1994 (Box 10)
  - La Donna Che Piangeva Sempre [original ms and typescript], undated (Box 11)
  - Essay on Steiner [copy], undated (Box 11)
  - Il Giorno del Ringraziamento, undated (Box 11)
  - Yale Italian Poetry, 1993, 1995, undated (Box 11)
  - Testi, 1999-2002 (Box 11)
  - Tradimenti [annotated draft], 1994 (Box 11)
  - Testi Regalati [with annotations], 1999 (Box 11)
  - Documenti Teatrali, 2004 (Box 11)
- Additional Material, Accession 2005-M-054
  - Yale Italian Poetry (YIP) correspondence [2 folders], 1992-2001 (Box 1)
  - Documenti Religiosi [XIV], 2003-2004 (Box 1)
  - Documenti Teatrali [XLII], 2004 (Box 1)
  - "Strega" documents, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Testi Regalati, 2004 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1995-2005; Accession 2006-M-001
  - Correspondence
    - Personal and professional, 2003 June-2004 July (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letteraria [XLII-XLV], 2003 March-December (Box 1, Folder 2 - 5)
    - Departmental, 2003 May-2004 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oberti Noguera, Natalia, "Reader's Report on Senior Essay", 2005 Mar, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Yalensia, 1995-1996, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Additional Material, 2004-2005; Accession 2006-M-025
  - Correspondence, personal, 2004 June-2005 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Documenti Teatrali [XLIII], 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 2002-2004; Accession 2006-M-114
  - Correspondence
    - Personal, 2002 December-2004 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letteraria [XLVI-XLIX], 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 5)
    - New York [I], 2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Additional Material, 2005; Accession 2007-M-006
  - Correspondence
    - Letteraria [L-LI], 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
    - New York [II], 2005 January-August (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Documenti Teatrali [XLIV], 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, 2005-2006; Accession 2007-M-062
  - Personal and literary correspondence, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 2007-2009; Accession 2011-M-006
  - Literary correspondence
    - 2007 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 2007 May-Sep (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 2007 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 2008 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 2008 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 2008 May-Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 2009 Jan-Aug (Box 1, Folder 7)